Finding Aid for Joseph Charles Satterthwaite papers, 1927-1961
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph Charles Satterthwaite papers 1927-1961
Satterthwaite, Joseph Charles, 1900-
2.2 linear feet
85365 Aa 2
Career foreign service officer from Tecumseh, Michigan. Correspondence, memoranda, and other papers concerning diplomatic assignments in Nepal, 1947, the Republic of South Africa, 1961-1965, and Argentina, Morocco, Burma, and Ceylon; and related photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Joseph C. Satterthwaite (donor no. 5253 ), chiefly in 1979.
The collection is open to research.
Joseph Satterthwaite was born in Tecumseh, Michigan March 4, 1900. He graduated from the University of Michigan (BA, 1923; MA, 1924), then commenced his career in the United States foreign service as a clerk in the consulate at Stuttgart, Germany. He became a Foreign Service Officer in 1926 and since then has served successively at Guadalajara, Mexico city, Buenos Aires, Baghdad, Ankara and Damascus. He was Personal Representative of the President with the rank of Minister on the Special United States Diplomatic Mission to the Kingdom of Nepal in 1947. In 1949, he was appointed Ambassador to Ceylon, remaining there until 1953 when he was transferred to Tangier, Morocco, as United States Diplomatic Agent with the rank of Minister. He was named Ambassador to Burma in 1955 and held that position until his return to Washington in 1957. In 1958, he was selected by President Eisenhower to the position of Assistant Secretary of State in the newly established Bureau of African Affairs. He served until 1961 when he was appointed to Ambassador to the Republic of South Africa, which position he held until 1965. He died December 19, 1990.
The Joseph Satterthwaite papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, and other papers concerning diplomatic assignments in Nepal, 1947, the Republic of South Africa, 1961-1965, and Argentina, Morocco, Burma, and Ceylon; and related photographs. The papers have been arranged into the following series: Personal/Biographical; Correspondence; Diplomatic Career; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Argentina.; Burma.; Sri Lanka.; Morocco.; Nepal.; South Africa.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States. Foreign service.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Cercle Français.; Clark, J. Reuben (Joshua Reuben), 1871-1961.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948.; Diplomats.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; International relations.; Mexico.; Morrow, Dwight W. (Dwight Whitney), 1873-1931.; Nu, U, 1907-1995; Nyerere, Julius K. (Julius Kambarage), 1922-1999.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal/Biographical
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
    (include press releases issued about him)
  - Speeches, statement to House Foreign Affairs Committee (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Personal (chronological)
    - Undated 1904 (Box 1)
    - 1928-1978, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Personal (alphabetical)
    (fragmentary)
    - 1950-1964
      - A (Box 1)
      - B, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - C (Box 1)
      - D (Box 1)
      - G (Box 1)
      - H (Box 1)
      - K (Box 1)
      - L (Box 1)
      - M (Box 1)
      - N (Box 1)
      - S (Box 1)
- Diplomatic Career
  - Diplomatic communications, statements, and reports 1927-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Assignments
    - Nepal 1947, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Nepal 1947, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs 1958-1959, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Republic of South Africa 1961-1965, 11 folders
      - Congratulatory letters (Box 2)
      - American Metal Climax, Inc. (Box 2)
      - B (Box 2)
      - D (Box 2)
      - Douglas, Lewis W. (Box 2)
      - E (Box 2)
      - F (Box 2)
      - H (Box 2)
      - J (Box 2)
      - S (Box 2)
      - Family, letters to 1962-1965 (Box 2)
    - Morocco and Tunisia (Box 2)
    - Burma, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Ceylon (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 9 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - American Foreign Service Association, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Brookings Conference for Career Executives 1957-1960 (Box 2)
  - Business Advisory Council, Department of Commerce (Box 2)
  - NASA 1967-1968 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Africa and African affairs (Box 3)
    (includes JCS with Averell Harriman and Julius Nyerere)
  - African United Nations representatives meet with Eisenhower October 14, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Burma (Box 3)
    (includes JCS with U Nu)
  - Friends and colleagues (Box 3)
    (includes JCS with G. Mennen Williams)
  - Egypt (Box 3)
  - Foreign Service Institute (Box 3)
  - Korea (Box 3)
  - Mexico
    - Morrow and Clark eras (to April 15, 1933)
      - Formal groups (Box 3)
      - Informal groups (Box 3)
    - Daniels era (from April 15, 1933)
      - Formal photos (Box 3)
      - Informal photos (Box 3)
  - Morocco (Box 3)
  - South Africa (Box 3)
  - Turkey (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    (includes Cercle Francais photo)